<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Tools</title>

  <para/>

  <section id="a_accountProfile">
    <title>Profile editor</title>

    <para>The account profiles are templates for your accounts. Here you can
    specify default values which can then be loaded when you create accounts.
    You may also load a template for an existing account to reset it to
    default values. When you create a new account then LAM will always load
    the profile named <emphasis role="bold">"default"</emphasis>. This account
    profile can include default values for all your accounts.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profileEditor2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>You can enter the LDAP suffix, RDN identifier and various other
    attributes depending on account type and activated modules.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profileEditor.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Import/export:</emphasis></para>

    <para>Profiles can be exported to and imported from other server
    profiles.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profileEditor3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profileEditor4.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>There is a special export target called "*Global templates". All
    profiles exported here will be copied to all other server profiles (incl.
    new ones). But existing profiles with the same name are not overwritten.
    So a profile in global templates is treated as default profile for all
    server profiles.</para>

    <para>Use this if you would like to setup default profiles that are valid
    for all server profiles.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/profileEditor5.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section id="tool_upload">
    <title>File upload</title>

    <para>When you need to create lots of accounts then you can use LAM's file
    upload to create them. In contrast to <link linkend="tool_upload">LDAP
    import/export</link> this operates on account type level.</para>

    <para>LAM will read a CSV formatted file and create the related LDAP
    entries. Please check the data in you CSV file carefully. LAM will do less
    checks for the file upload than for single account creation.</para>

    <para>At the first page please select the account type and what extensions
    should be activated.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/fileUpload1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The next page shows all available options for the file upload. You
    will also find a sample CSV file which can be used as template for your
    CSV file. All red options are required columns in the file. You need to
    specify a value for each account.</para>

    <para>When you upload the CSV file then LAM first does some checks on this
    file. This includes syntax checks and if all required data was entered. No
    changes in the LDAP directory are done at this time.</para>

    <para>If the checks were successful then LAM will ask again if you want to
    create the accounts. You will also have the chance to check the upload by
    viewing the changes in LDIF format.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/fileUpload2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="toolMultiEdit">Multi edit</title>

    <para>This tool allows you to modify a large list of LDAP entries in batch
    mode. You can add new attributes/object classes, remove attributes and set
    attributes to a specific value.</para>

    <para>At the beginning, you need to specify where the entries are stored
    that should be changed. You can select an account suffix, the tree suffix
    or enter your own DN by selecting "Other".</para>

    <para>Next, enter an additional LDAP filter to limit the entries that
    should be changed. E.g. use "(objectclass=inetOrgPerson)" to filter for
    users. You may also enter e.g. "(!(objectClass=passwordSelfReset))" to
    match all accounts that do not yet have the <link
    linkend="passwordSelfResetUser">password self reset</link> feature.</para>

    <literallayout>
</literallayout>

    <para>Now, it is time to define the changes that should be done. The
    following operations are possible:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add: Adds an attribute value if not yet existing. Please do not
        use for single-value attributes that already have a value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Modify: Sets an attribute to the given value. If the attribute
        does not yet exist then it is added. If the attribute has multiple
        values then all other values are removed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Delete: Deletes the specified value from this attribute. If you
        leave the value field blank then all attribute values are
        removed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Please note that all actions are run as separate LDAP commands. You
    cannot add an object class and a required attribute at the same
    time.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/multiEdit1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Dry run</emphasis></para>

    <para>You should always start with a dry run. It will not do any changes
    to your LDAP directory but print out all modifications that will be done.
    You will also be able to download the changes in LDIF format to use with
    ldapmodify. This is useful if you want to adjust some actions
    manually.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/multiEdit2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Apply changes</emphasis></para>

    <para>This will run the actions against your LDAP directory. You will see
    which accounts are edited in the progress area and also if any errors
    occured.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/multiEdit3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section id="tool_importexport">
    <title>LDAP import/export</title>

    <para>Here you can import and export plain LDAP data. In contrast to <link
    linkend="tool_upload">file upload</link> this operates on plain LDAP
    attribute level.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Import</title>

      <para>The LDAP import supports input data in <ulink
      url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LDAP_Data_Interchange_Format">LDIF</ulink>
      format. You can provide plain text or upload an LDIF file.</para>

      <para>The "Don't stop on errors" option will cause the import to
      continue even if entries could not be created.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="images/tool_import.png"/>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Export</title>

      <para>Here you can export your plain LDAP data as LDIF or CSV
      file.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="images/tool_export.png"/>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Base DN: this is the starting point of the export. Enter a DN or
      press the magnifying glass icon to open the DN selection dialog.</para>

      <para>Search scope: You can export just the base DN, base DN + its
      direct children or the whole subtree.</para>

      <para>Search filter: this can be used to filter the entries by
      specifying a standard LDAP filter. The preselected filter
      "(objectclass=*)" matches all entries.</para>

      <para>Attributes: the list of attributes that should be part of export.
      "*" matches all standard attributes (excluding system
      attributes).</para>

      <para>Include system attributes: this will also include system
      attributes like the entry creation time and creator's DN.</para>

      <para>Save as file: will save to file instead of printing the data on
      the web page.</para>

      <para>Export format: you can select LDIF or CSV (e.g. for usage in
      spreadsheet applications).</para>

      <para>End of line: use the one appropriate for your operating
      system.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>OU editor</title>

    <para>This is a simple editor to add/delete organisational units in your
    LDAP tree. This way you can structure the accounts.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ouEditor.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section id="pdfEditor">
    <title>PDF editor</title>

    <para>All accounts in LAM may be exported as PDF files. You can specify
    the page structure and displayed information by editing the PDF
    profiles.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>When you export accounts to PDF then each account will get its own
    page inside the PDF. There is a headline on each page where you can show a
    page title. You may also add a logo to each page. To add more logos please
    use the logo management on the PDF editor main page.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The main part is structured into sections of information. Each
    section has a title. This can either be static text or the value of an
    attribute. You may also insert a static text block as section. Sections
    can be moved by using the arrows next to the section title.</para>

    <para>Each section can contain multiple fields which usually represent
    LDAP attributes. You can simply add new fields by selecting the field name
    and its position. Then use the arrows to move the field inside the
    section.</para>

    <literallayout>
</literallayout>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Import/export:</emphasis></para>

    <para>PDF structures can be exported to and imported from other server
    profiles.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor4.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>There is a special export target called "*Global templates". All PDF
    structures exported here will be copied to all other server profiles
    (incl. new ones). But existing PDF structures with the same name are not
    overwritten. So a PDF structure in global templates is treated as default
    structure for all server profiles.</para>

    <para>Use this if you would like to setup default PDF structures that are
    valid for all server profiles.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor5.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Logo management:</emphasis></para>

    <para>You can upload image files to put a custom logo on the PDF files.
    The image file name must end with .png or .jpg.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/pdfEditor6.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Schema browser</title>

    <para>Here you browse the schema of your LDAP server. You can view what
    object classes, attributes, syntaxes and matching rules are available.
    This is useful if you need to check if a certain object class is
    available.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/schemaBrowser.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Server information</title>

    <para>This shows information and statistics about your LDAP server. This
    includes the suffixes, used overlays, connection data and operation
    statistics. You will need "cn=monitor" setup to see all details. Some data
    may not be available depending on your LDAP server software.</para>

    <para>Please see the following links how to setup "cn=monitor":</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.openldap.org/doc/admin24/monitoringslapd.html">OpenLDAP</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink type=""
        url="http://directory.fedoraproject.org/wiki/Howto:CN%3DMonitor_LDAP_Monitoring">389
        server</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/serverInfo.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="tool_webauthn">Webauthn devices</title>

    <para>Here you can manage your webauthn/FIDO2 devices.</para>

    <para>You can register additional security devices and remove old ones. If
    no more device is registered then LAM will ask you for registration on
    next login.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="images/tool_webauthn1.png"/>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tests</title>

    <para>This allows you to check if your LDAP schema is compatible with LAM
    and to find possible problems.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Lamdaemon test</title>

      <para>LAM provides an external script to manage home directories and
      quotas. You can test here if everything is setup correctly.</para>

      <para>If you get an error like "no tty present and no askpass program
      specified" then the path to the lamdaemon.pl may be wrong. Please see
      the <link linkend="a_lamdaemon">lamdaemon installation
      instructions</link> for setup details.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/lamdaemonTest.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Schema test</title>

      <para>This will test if your LDAP schema supports all object classes and
      attributes of the active LAM modules. If you get a message that
      something is missing please check that you installed all <link
      linkend="a_schema">required schemas</link>.</para>

      <para>If you get error messages about object class violations then this
      test can tell you what is missing.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/schemaTest.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
